Guide to the William North Rice Papers, 1861 - 1955 (bulk 1861 - 1928)
William North Rice Papers, 1861 - 1955 (bulk 1861 - 1928)
- Series 3. Publications, Addresses, and Sermons, 1867-1955 (bulk 1867-1927)
  - Education
    - Wesleyan University, Meeting of the Connecticut Association of Classical and High School Teachers, 16 February 1901 (Folder 4)
    - The Proper Scope of Geological Teaching in the High School and Academy, a paper read at the meeting of the National Educational Association at Boston, MA, July 1903
    - The Sciences speech, Connecticut Association of Classical and High School Teachers, 1904
    - The Pastoral Opportunity of the College Professor, Christian Student, Vol. VI, No. 1, February 1905
    - State Universities and the Church, Christian Student, Vol. VI, No. 4, November 1905
    - A Danger Arising from the Popularization of the College, Science, Vol. XXXIX, No. 749, 5 March 1909
    - The College Course, Christian Student, Vol. XI, No. 1, February 1910 (Folder 5)
    - The Call to Teach, Christian Education, Vol. V, No. 9, June 1922
    - Science Teaching in the Schools, American Naturalist, September-October 1888
    - Newspaper articles, 1898-1910 and undated
  - Geology and Science
    - Introduction to Natural Science, course outline, undated (Folder 6)
    - Geological Notes of the Senior Excursion, College Argus, 24 November 1869
    - On the Effects of Certain Poisons on Mollusks, from Proceedings of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Portland Meeting, August 1873
    - The Geology of Middlesex County, from History of Middlesex County, 1884
    - The Geology of Bermuda, from Bulletin No. 25, U.S. National Museum, 1884
    - On the Trap and Sandstone in the Gorge of the Farmington River at Tariffville, Conn., American Journal of Science, Vol. XXXII, December 1886
    - Discovery of Rutile in North Guilford, Observer, January 1890
    - The Degree of Probability of Scientific Beliefs, New Englander and Yale Review, January 1891 (Folder 7)
    - Twenty-Five Years of Scientific Progress, Bibliotheca Sacra, Vol. L, January 1893
    - Remarks on the Petrographic Excursion, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, vol. 8, 1896
    - Review of The Principles of Museum Administration by G. Brown Goode, in Science, 22 May 1896
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, Section E, Geology and Geography, Science, 18 September 1896
    - Geology and Mineralogy, The Smithsonian Institution, 1846-1896, the History of its First Half-Century, 1897
    - Glacial Period, Popular Science, March 1899
    - Scientific Thought in the Nineteenth Century, Science, Vol. X, No. 261, 29 December 1899
    - Scientific Thought in the Nineteenth Century, an address delivered at the centennial anniversary of the Academy, Transactions of the Academy, 1903
    - The Proper Scope of Geological Teaching in the High School and Academy, Proceedings of the National Education Association, 1903
    - The Physical Geography and Geology of Connecticut, Report of Connecticut Board of Agriculture, 1903
    - Convocation Week, Science, Vol. XIX, No. 483, 1 April 1904 (Folder 8)
    - On the Use of the Words Synclinorium and Anticlinorium, Science, Vol. XXIII, 23 February 1906
    - The Contributions of America to Geology, Proceedings of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Vol. XXXI, April-May 1911
    - Dana, the Man, Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, Vol. 24, 1912
    - James Dwight Dana, Yale Alumni Weekly, 3 January 1913
    - Yakutat Bay, Wesleyan Liberary Monthly, February 1914
    - Peat in Connecticut, Guide to Nature, Vol. XIV, No. 4, September 1921
    - The New Geology, Methodist Review, July-August 1924
  - Religion and Theology
    - Sermons, circa 1880-1900 (Folder 9)
    - Sermons, circa 1880-1900 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Can a Good Catholic be a Darwinian? proof with corrections, undated (Folder 3)
    - Address in Installation Services of Reverend John L. R. Trask as Pastor of Memorial Church, 1888
    - A Symposium Upon the Advisability of a Normal Department in Theological Seminaries, by W. N. Rice et al, The Old and New Testament Student, Vol. XI, No. 2, August 1890
    - The Credibility of the Resurrection of Jesus, Methodist Review, March-April 1895
    - Paleontology and Evolution (November 10) and The Credibility of Miracle (November 17) in University Extension Lectures, 1898-1899
    - Recent Phases of Thought in Apologetics, Methodist Review, January-February 1899
    - The Return to Faith, Wesleyan Argus, 4 April 1900
    - The YMCA and the Churches, Middletown Men, pamphlet of YMCA of Middletown, May 1904
    - Baccalaureate Sermon, Wesleyan Argus, 7 July 1909
    - Professor Rice Reviews Epoch Marking Book, (Origin and History of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, by Elias B. Sanford), The Wesleyan Alumnus, July 1917
    - Several articles in Minutes of the New York East Annual Conference, April 1919
    - Through Doubt to Faith, Wesleyan University Alumnus, May 1923
    - Religious newspaper articles, 1867-1925 (Folder 4-10)
    - Religious certificates, 1864-1872 (Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Folder 12)
    Includes articles on temperence, politics, and obituaries